<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An acte for the hauynge of horsse, armour and weapon</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1558</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33149701</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33149701</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28472</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21571)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1874:49)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An acte for the hauynge of horsse, armour and weapon</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>Mary I, Queen of England, 1516-1558.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1553-1558 : Mary I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7 leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Iohannis Cavvodi Tipographi Regiæ Maiestatis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1558]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains wood-cut initial.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Military readiness --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Mary I, 1553-1558.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="Act_of_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:28472:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN ACTE</hi> for the hauynge of Horſſe, Armour and Weapon.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR THE BETTER</hi> furniture and defence of this realme. Be it enacted by the kynge and Quenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties with thaſſentes of the lords ſpiritual and temporal, and the commons in thys preſent Parliamente aſſembled, and by aucthorytie of the ſame, that aſmuch of al and euerye acte and Statute concernyng onely the kepyng or finding of horſe, horſes or armoure, or of anye of them heretofore made or prouided, and al and euery forfeyture and penaltie concernyng onely the ſame, ſhalbe from henceforth vtterly voyd repealed &amp; of none effecte.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that euerye noble man gentelman and other temporall perſonne, after the rate and proportion hereafter decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſhall haue and kepe in a redines ſuch horſſes, geldinges, armour and other furniture for the warres, at the feaſt, and in ſuch ſort and maner as is and ſhalbe in thys Acte, here after expreſſed and declared. That is to ſaye, all and euery perſonne temporall, hauynge anye honors, lordeſhyppes, manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures or woodes, of eſtate of inheritaunce or frehold, to the clere yearelye value of one thouſande pounde or aboue, ſhall from and after the firſt day of May which ſhalbe in the yeare of our lord God a thouſande fyue hundred fyfty and eyght, haue, finde, kepe, ſuſteine and meinteine wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thys realme of Englande, of their owne proper and at their owne proper coſtes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences .vi. horſſes or geldinges, able for dymylaunces, wherof three of them at the leaſte to be horſſes, with ſufficient harneſſes, ſteele ſaddels, &amp; weapon, requiſite and aperteyning to the ſayde dymylaunces, horſes or geldynges, and tenne lyghte horſſes or geldynges able and mete for light horſemen, with the furniture of harnes and weapon requiſit for the ſame, and alſo fourtye corſelettes furniſhed, fourty almayne ryuettes or in ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſayd almayne ryuettes, fourtye cotes of plate, corſelettes or brygandynes furnyſhed, fourtye pykes, thyrtye longe bowes, thyrtye ſhefes of arrowes, thyrtye ſteele cappes or ſculles, twentye blacke bylles or halbertes, twenty haquebuttes, &amp; twenty morians or ſallettes. And euery perſon temporall hauynge any honors, lordſhyppes, manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures, or woddes, of any ſuche eſtate as is aforeſayd, to the clere yearelye value of a thouſande markes or aboue, and vnder the cleare yearely value of a thouſande pounde, ſhal haue, finde, ſuſtayne, and mayntayne, wythin this Realme of theyr owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and at their owne proper coſtes and expences, fowre horſes, or geldynges, able for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milaunces, whereof two at the leaſte to be horſes, wyth ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t harneſſes and weapon and ſadels mete and requiſite to the ſayd dimilaunces, horſes or geldinges, and ſixe light hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or geldynges able and mete for light horſemen, with furniture of harnes and weapon requiſite for the ſame. And alſo of armoure and weapon thyrtye corſelettes furnyſhed, thyrtye almayne ryuyttes, or in ſtede of the ſayd almayne ryuettes, thyrty cotes of plate, corſelettes or brygandynes furnyſhed, thyrty pykes, twenty longe bowes, twenty ſhefes of arrowes, twenty ſteele cappes or ſculles, ten blacke billes or halberdes, ten haquebuts, and tenne moryans or ſallettes. And euery perſon temporal hauing honors, lordſhippes, manoures, houſes, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, medowes, paſtures, or woddes, of any ſuch eſtate as is aforeſaid to the clere yearely value of fowre hundrethe poundes or aboue, and vnder the cleare yearelye value of a thouſande markes, ſhall haue, fynd, kepe, ſuſtayne, and mayntayne, as
<pb facs="tcp:28472:2"/>is aforeſayd, two horſes, or one horſe &amp; one geldyng able for dymylaunces, with ſufficient furniture of harnes ſteele ſadels &amp; weapon for the ſame as is aforeſaid, &amp; fowre geldynges able forlyght horſemen, wyth ſufficient harnes and weapon for the ſame, and alſo .xx. cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelettes furnyſhed .xx. almayne riuettes furniſhed, or in ſtede of almayne riuettes twenty cotes of plate corſelettes or brigandines furnyſhed, twenty pykes, fyftene longe bowes fyftene ſhefes of arrowes, fyftene ſteele cappes or ſculles, ſyxe haquebuttes, and ſyre mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryans or ſalletes. And that euery perſon temporal hauying lordſhyppes, manors, houſes landes medowes, paſtures or woodes, of anye ſuche eſtate as is aforeſayde, to the cleare yearely value of .C C. poundes or aboue, and vnder the cleare yearelye value of .C C C C. poundes, ſhal from the ſaid fyrſt day of May, haue, kepe, ſuſteine and maintaine one gret horſe or geldynge, able for a dimilaunce, with ſufficient furniture of harnes, ſteeled ſadle, and weapon for the ſame, &amp; two geldinges, able for lyght horſemen, with harnes and wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pons ſuffiryent, as is aforeſayde, for the ſame, and alſo ten corſelettes furnyſhed, tenne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne ryuettes, or in the place of almayne riuyttes, ten cotes of plate, corſelettes or bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandynes furniſhed, ten pykes, eyght longe bowes, eyght ſhefes of arrowes, eyght ſteele cappes or ſcules thre haquebuttes, and three morians or ſallettes. And euery perſon tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall hauynge any lordeſhyppes, manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures, or wodes of anye ſuch eſtate as is aforeſayd, to the clere yearelye value of one hundred poundes, or aboue, and vnder the yearely value of two hundred poundes, ſhall from and after the ſayd fyrſt daye of Maye, haue, kepe, and mayntayne (as is aforeſayd) two geldynges, able and mete for light horſemen, with ſufficient harnes, and weapon requiſite for the ſame. And al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo three corſeletes furnyſhed, three almayne ryuyttes, or in ſtede of them ſoo manye cotes of plate, corſelettes, or brygandines furnyſhed, three pykes, three longe bowes, three ſhefes of arrowes, three ſteele cappes or ſeulles, two haquebuttes, and two morians or ſal lettes. And alſo euery perſon temporall hauyng lordeſhyppes, manoures, houſes, landes meadowes, paſtures, or woodes of anye ſuch eſtate as is aforeſayd, to the clere yearelye value of a hundred markes or aboue, and vnder the yearely value of a hundrede poundes, from the ſayde firſt day of May, ſhall haue, kepe, maynteine and ſuſteyne one gelding able and mete for alyght horſeman, with the harnes and weapon ſuffycyent and requiſyte for the ſame two corſelettes furniſhed, two almaine ryuittes, or in ſtede of the ſame two cotes of plate, or brygandynes furnyſhed, two pykes, two longe bowes, two ſhefes of arrowes, two ſteele cappes or ſculles, one haquebut, one moryan or ſallet. And alſo euery perſon te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall hauynge lordeſhyppes, manors houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures or woodes, of anye ſuche eſtate as is aforeſayde, to the yerely value of fourty poundes or aboue, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the yearely value of a hundred markes, ſhal from and after the ſayd fyrſt day of May haue, mayntayne and kepe two corſelettes furnyſhed, two almayne riuettes, or in ſteede of the ſame, two cotes of plate, corſelettes or brygandines furnyſhed, two pikes, one long bowe, one ſhefe of arrowes, one ſteele cap or ſcull .ii. haquebuts two morians or ſalletes. And alſo euery perſon temporall hauinge lordſhypes, manoures, houſes, lands, medowes paſtures or wodes, of any ſuch eſtate as is aforeſaid, to the cleare yerely value of twenty poundes or aboue, and vnder the yearely value of .xi. poundes, ſhall from the ſayde fyrſte daye of Maye, haue, kepe, and maynetaine, one corſelet furniſhed, one pike, one haquebut, one morian or ſallet, one longe bowe, one ſhefe of arrowes, and one ſteele cappe or ſcull.</p>
            <p>And alſo euery perſonne temporall hauynge lordeſhyps, manoures, houſes, landes, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, paſtures, or wodes, of any ſuche eſtate as is aforeſayde, to the cleare yearely value of tenne poundes, or aboue, and vnder the yearelye value of .xx. pounde, ſhal from and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſayd daye haue, kepe, and ſuſtayne, one almayne ryuitte, cote of plate or brigandine furniſhed, one haquebut, one morian or ſallet, and one long bowe, and one ſhefe of arrowes
<pb facs="tcp:28472:3"/>one ſteele cap or ſcull. And alſo euery perſon temporall hauyng lordſhyps, manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures or woodes, of ſuche eſtate as is aforeſayde, to the clere year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye value of fyue poundes or aboue, and vnder the yearelye value of tenne poundes, ſhall from and after the ſayde fyrſte daye of Maye haue, kepe, and ſuſtayne, one cote of plate fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed, one blacke byll or halberte, one longe bowe, one ſhefe of arrowes, and one ſteele cap or ſcull. And alſo euery perſon temporall hauynge gooddes or cattels to the value of one thouſande markes or aboue, ſhall from the ſayde fyrſte daye of Maye haue, fynde, kepe, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne, and mayntayne, as is aforeſayde one horſe or geldinge hable for a dimilaunce, with ſufficient harnes ſteele ſadell and weapon requiſite and conuenyente for the ſame, and one geldynge able and mete for alyght horſeman wyth harnes and weapon ſufficyent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite as is aforeſayde for the ſame, or eyghtence cerſelettes furnyſhed, in the ſtede of the ſayde horſe, and geſdynge, and furniture of the ſame at hys choyſe. And alſo ſhal from the ſame daye haue, fynde, kepe, &amp; mayntayue of armor and weapon, two corſelets furniſhed, two almaine ryuettes, or for the ſame almainryuets, two cotes of plate, two corſelettes, or two brigandynes furnyſhed, two pykes, foure longe bowes, foure ſhefe of arrowes, foure ſteele cappes or ſculles, &amp; thre haquebuttes, wyth .iii. morians, or ſallettes. And alſo euery perſon temporall hauynge goodes or cattels, to the values hereafter in thys preſent acte ſpecified and declared, ſhall from and after the ſayde ſyrſte daye of Maye haue finde, kepe, ſuſtayne and mayntayne ſuch geldynges, armoure, weapon, and furniture for warre as is hereafter declared. That is to ſaye, hauynge to the value of foure hundrede poundes or aboue, and vnder the value of a thouſande mackes, one geldynge able &amp; meete for a lyght horſeman wyth ſufficient harnes and weapon requiſite and mete for the ſame, or nine cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelettes, furnyſhed at hys election, and alſo ſhall haue, fynde, and kepe one other corſelette furnyſhed, one pyke, two almayne riuetes, or plate cotes or brigandines furniſhed, one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebut, two longe bowes, two ſhefes of arrowes, and two ſtele cappes or ſculles. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng in gooddes and cattels, to the value of two hundred poundes or aboue, and vnder foure hundred, one corſelet furnyſhed, one pyke, two almayne ryuetes, plate cotes, or bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandines furnyſhed, one haquebut, one murryan or ſalet, two longe bowes and two ſoefe of arrowes, and two ſculles or ſteele cappes. And hauyng in goodes and cattels to the va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lue of a hundred poundes or aboue and vnder two hundred poundes, one corſelette furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and one pyke, one payre of almayne ryuyttes, one plate cote, or payre of brygandines furnyſhed, two longe bowes, and two ſhefes of arrowes, and two ſculles. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge as is aforeſayde, in goodes and ratteſes, to the value of fourtye poundes, or aboue, and vnder a hundred poundes, two payre of almain ryuittes, or two cotes of plate or brygandines furniſhed, one long bowe, and one ſhefe of arrowes, one ſtele cappe or ſcull, and one blacke byll, or halbert. And hauyng as is aforeſayd in goodes and cattelles to the value of twenty poundes or aboue, and vnder .xl. poundes, one payre of almaine riuetes, or one cote of plate, or one payre of brygandines, two long bewes, two ſhefes of arrowes .ii. ſculles or ſtecle cappes, and one blacke byll or halbert. And hauynge as is aforeſayd to the value of tenne poundes or aboue, and vnder twentye poundes, one longe bowe, one ſhefe of arrowes with one ſteele cappe or ſcull, and one blacke bill or halberte. And alſo that euery perſon temporall not beyng aboue charged by thys acte: hauyng or that hereafter ſhal haue any Innuitie, or annuities, or yerely fee or fees, for terme of life, or of any eſtate of enheritaunce or anye copyholde, or copyholdes for terme of lyfe, or of anye eſtate of enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce to the clere yerely value of .xxx. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des or aboue, ſhalbe charged and chargeable w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche furniture of warre, as is aforeſayde, ineuerye degree, qualytye, and condition, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the proportions and rates before expreſſed, limitted and appointed for goodes and cattelles.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28472:4"/>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that euery perſonne whiche by vertue of thacte made in the Parliament holden at Weſtmiuſter in the .xxxiii. yeare of the reygne of kyng Henry theyght, was bound (by reſon that his wyfe ſhuld weare ſuch kind of apparell or other thing, as in the ſame Statute is ſpecially mentioned and declared) to kepe or fynde one greate ſtoned trottinge horſe, and is not by this acte before charged to haue mayntayne and kepe any horſe or geldynge, ſhall from the ſayde firſte day of Maye, haue, kepe, and mayntayne one geldynge able and mete for alyght horſeman, with ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent harnes and weapon for the ſame, in ſuch maner and forme, as euerye temporall perſon hauynge lordeſhyps, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures or woodes of ſuche eſtate as is aforeſayde, of the clere yerely value of one hundred markes, is charged or appoynted, to fynde, haue, and mayntayne by thys preſent acte.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the auctoritye aforeſayd, that yf any perſon chargeable by thys acte, as is aforeſayde, ſhall by the ſpace of any thre whole monethes after the ſayd fyrſt daye of Maye, lacke or wante the ſayde number and kyndes of horſes, geldinges, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, weapon, and furniture aforeſaide, or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, after ſuche rate, proportion, maner, and fourme as is in thys acte aboue limited, declared, and appoynted. That then euerye ſuche perſon ſhall forfeyte and loſe for euery ſuche thre monethes that he ſhall ſo lacke and want the ſame number and kyndes of horſes, geldynges, armure, weapon, and furniture, or any parte therof, for euery horſe or geldynge ſo lackinge tenne poundes. And for euery dymylaunce and furniture of the ſame thre poundes, and for euery corſelet and furniture of the ſame .xi. s. And for euery almayne ryuet, cote of plate, or brigandine, and the furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſame .xx. s. And for euerye bowe and ſhefe of arrowes, byll, halbert, haquebut, ſteelecappe, ſcull, morryan, and fallet .x. s. the one moytye of whych ſayde forfeytures ſhal be to the Kyng and Quene our ſoueraigne Lorde and Lady, and to theirs and ſucceſſors of the ſame our ſoueraygne Lady. And the other moytie to him or them that wyll ſue for the ſame, in any courte of recorde, by byll, playnt, action of debt, or information, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which byll, playnt, action, or information, no wager of lawe, eſſoygne or protection ſhalbe allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or admytted.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that the inhabytauntes of eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry citye, borough, towne, paryſhe and hamlette within this realme, other then ſuch as are ſpecially charged before in thys act, ſhal haue, finde, kepe, ſuſteine, and mayntayne at theyr common charges and expenſes, ſuch harnes and weapon, and aſmuch thereof as ſhalbe ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poynted by the commyſſioners of our ſayde ſoueraygne lorde and lady, and of the heires and ſucceſſoures of the ſame our ſoueraygne Lady, for the muſters or vewe of ar moure within ſuch Cytye, Burroughe, Towne, Paryſhe or Hamlette, there to be kept in ſuche place, as by the ſayde commiſſyoners ſhalbe appoynted. And the numbers &amp; kyndes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be wrytten and compryſed in a payre of indentures, to be made betwene the ſayd com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſioners or two of them at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt, and twelue, eyght, or foure, of the cheyfeſte of euerye ſuche Cytye, Burroughe, Towne, Paryſhe or Hamlette, whereof one parte to remaine with the cheife officer of the ſame Cytye, Burroughe, Towne, Paryſhe or Hamlette. And the other parte to remayne with the clerke of the peace of the ſhyre or countye where euery ſuche Citye, Towne, Burrough, Paryſhe, or Hamlet, ſhall ſtande or be. And yf the ſame inhabytauntes of euerye ſuche Citye, Borough, Towne, Paryſhe, or Hamlet, other then ſuche as are ſpeciallye (as is afore ſayd) charged, ſhall lacke or wante ſuche harnes or weapons, or any parte therof, as ſhall be vnto them appoynted by the ſaid Commiſſioners for the muſters or vewe of armoure, as is aforeſayd, by the ſpace of any three monethes to gether next after any ſuch apointment made. That then the ſame inhabitauntes ſhal for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyte for euery the ſayde three monethes, for euery ſuch harnes or weapons ſo lackyng, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:28472:5"/>the rate aboue limytted, the one moytie therof to be to our ſayde Soueraygne lorde and lady, and to theires and ſucceſſoures of our ſaid ſoueraygne lady. And thother moytie to hym or them that wyl ſue for the ſame, in any of the courtes of recorde of our ſayd So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraygne lorde and lady, and of theirs and Succeſſoures of the ſame oure Soueraygne ladye, by byll, playnt, action of debte, or information wherein no wager of lawe, eſſoygne or protection, ſhalbe admitted or allowed.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the authoritie aforeſayd, that the Lord Chauncelloure of Englande, for the tyme beyng, ſhall haue full power and auctoritie by vertue of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t act, from time to tyme, to graunt out commyſſyons, vnder the gret ſeale of England, to the Iuſtyers of Peace, within euery Sheire, or countye of thys realme, or to ſo many of them as by hys diſcretion ſhalbe thought mete and conuenient, for the apointing and lymitting of the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yd harneſſes and weapons, to be found kept and mainteined in euery ſuch Cytye, Burroughe, Towne, Paryſhe, and Hamlette, at the common charges of thinhabitauntes thereof as is aforeſayd.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes that thys acte or any thyng therein conteyned ſhall not extend to take awaye or diſcharge any tenaunt or fermour, of hys ſeruyce or couenaunt towardes hys lord for the fyndyng of horſe, armoure, or weapon, or for doing of ſeruice by him ſelfe or anye other, whych, by the tenure of his lande, or ferme, he is bounde to do, at the tyme of makynge of thys acte. But that he ſhall yelde, paye, and doe the ſame in as large ample maner and forme as though this acte had neuer bene had ne made.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the auctoritye aforeſayd, that the Iuſtices of peace of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye Shyre, ſhall haue power and auctoritye by vertue of thys acte, from tyme to tyme to make ſearche and vewe, of and for the ſayde furnitures of horſes, geldynges, armure and weapon, to be found, mayntained, and kepte, by any perſon aboue ſayde, hauyng lord ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, manours, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures, or woddes, to the clere yearely value of. CC. poundes or vnder, &amp; not aboue the yerely value of. CCCC. poundes, or to be found mayntayned or kepte, by any perſonne or perſons chargeable by this acte, by reaſon of his or theyr gooddes, catteles, annuities, fees, or coppyhoſdes, as is aforeſayde, and to here and determyne at their quarter ſeſſions al and euerye the defaultes committed or done contrary to thys acte, within the countye where ſuch Seſſions ſhalbe kept, by inquiſition preſentment, byll, or information, before them exhibited, or by examination of two lawefull witnes, at the diſcretion of the ſame Iuſtices, and to award proces thervpon as thoughe they were indicted before them by verdicte of twelue men or more. And vpon the conuyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the offender, by information or ſute of any other then the kynge or the quene, or of theires or Succeſſoures of the quene, to make eſtreates of thone moytie of the ſayd for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feytures to be leuied to thuſe of our ſayde ſoueraygne Lord and lady, or of theires or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſoures of the ſame our Soueraygne lady, as they vſe to do of other fynes, iſſues, and amercyamentes, growing in the ſeſſyons of peace. And to awarde execution of thother moytie for the complaynaunte or informer agaynſt the offender, by fieri facias or capias, as the kynges Iuſtices at Weſtminſter maye doo and vſe to do. And yf any ſuch conuicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall hereafter happen at thonely ſute of our ſayd ſoueraygne lorde and ladye, or of the heires or ſucceſſoures of the ſame our ſoueraygne lady, that then the whole forfeytures to be eſtreated and leuyed to their vſes onely.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſaid, that whenſoeuer any perſon ſhal at any tyme hereafter be conuicted by vertue of thys acte for any default or thynge men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in thys acte, that then the ſame perſonne ſhall not otherwyſe or eftſones be vexed, troubeled, ſued, or conuicted, for the ſame defaulte or thyng, wherefore he ſhall be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uycted. ¶ And be it moreouer enacted by thauctorytye aforeſayd, that yf any ſouldioure
<pb facs="tcp:28472:6"/>ſhall at any tyme hereafter make ſale of his horſe, harnes, and weapon, or any of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the fourme of the ſayde ſtatute made in the ſaide ſeconde and thyrd yeares of the ſayde late kynge, that then not onelye the ſame Souldiour ſhall incurre the penaltyes of that ſtatute, but alſo the ſayde ſale made by ſuche Souldiour to anye perſon or perſons knowing him to be a ſouldier, ſhall be voyde and of none effecte, agaynſt hym or them that founde or ſet forthe the ſayde horſe, harnes, and weapon, or any of them, to or for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyture of ſuche ſouldior to ſerue wyth the ſame.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes that no perſonne ſhall be impeached or trowbled for any offence done contrary to this act, onles preſentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or ſute therof be had, made, or take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wythin one yeare next after the offence done, any thyng in thys act to the contrary therof in any wyſe notwythſtandynge.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwaye and be it enacted by thauctoritye aforeſayd, that yf at any tyme hereafter it ſhall fortune any perſon or perſons aforeſaid, to be ſued or impeached for any forfayture or penaltye, for not hauyng, ſuſteyning, or kepyng ſuche furniture of corſelet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, pykes, haquebuttes, or moryans, as by this acte is before limyted, rated, and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and for his or their excuſe and aunſwer ſhall alleage and pleade that the ſame furny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo lackynge, could not by hym or them conueniently be hadde gotten or prouyded, for want and lacke of the ſame within this realme, accordynge to the tenure and purport of thys acte, the ſame matter of want and lacke as is aforeſayde, ſhalbe allowed, and taken for a good and ſufficiente anſwere and barre in the lawe, in caſe it be true, and yf the ſame be denyed or trauerſed, that thervpon an iſſue ſhall be ioyned, and that the tryall ſhall be of euery ſuche iſſue onely had by the certificate to be made by the Lorde Chauncellor, Lorde Treaſurer, the Lorde preſident of the Councell, the Lorde Steward of the Kynges and Quenes moſte honorable houſeholde, the Lorde Priuie Seale, the Lorde Admirall, and the lorde Chamberlaine of the ſayd houſehold, or by thre of them, in wryting vnder their reales, or the ſeales of three of them, thys preſentacte, or any ſtatute lawe or vſage hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alſo and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that no perſon or perſons chargeable by vertue of thys acte, to or for the fyndyng or hauyng of any horſe, geldyng, armoure, weapon, or furniture for the warre as is aforeſayd, ſhalbe charged with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame, or with any of them both, for his manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures &amp; woodes, and alſo for his goodes, cattels, fermes, leaſes, copyholdes, rentes, annuities.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alſo and be it further enacted by thauethoritie aforeſaid, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this acte or any thing therein co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned, ſhal not in any wiſe extend or be adiudged, or interpreted to abro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gate, repeale, or make voyd, any part, ſentence, matter, clauſe, article, or thing conteyned, or ſpecifyed in the ſtatute, made in the .xxxiii. yeare of the raygne of the late noble Prince of worthy memorye kyng Henry the .viii. for or concernyng the hauyng of longe bowes, and arrowes, and the vſing, order, exercyſyng, and mayntenaunce of archery, and ſhoting in long bowes, but that the ſame ſtatute and euery article, clauſe, ſentence and thing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conteyned and ſpecified, touching, or in any wyſe concernyng the hauyng of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g bowes, arrowes, vſyng, order, exerciſing, or maintenaunce of archery, and ſhoting in long bowes, ſhal ſtande and remayne in force, and be obſerued, perſourmed, and kept, according to the tenure effect and true meanynge of the ſayd acte, vppon the paynes conteyned in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame, as this acte had not bene had ne made, thys preſent acte or any thynge therin conteyned to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alſo that yf it ſhall fortune the ſayde furnyture of Armoure aforeſayde, or any parte therof, at any tyme hereafter to be loſt or ſpent in any ſeruyce of defence of thys realme, or elles the horſſes, or geldynges aforeſayde, to be kylled or dyſtroyed, or elles by
<pb facs="tcp:28472:7"/>ſome other occaſion to be dead, that in ſuch caſe or caſes, no perſon or perſons, ſhalbe char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with any forfeyture or penaltye aforeſayd, for not hauynge ſuch quantitye or number of armoure, horſes or geldinges, as is aforeſayd, ſo that he or they within one yere next af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ſuch loſſe or want, do ſupplye the ſame agayne, in all pointes, according to the true mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge and purport of thys acte, any thing in the ſame act to the contrary therof notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alſo that the want of any gauntlet or gauntletttes, ſhall not be deamed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted, or taken for anye lacke or want of furneiture for acorſelet, any wordes before ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſed ſoundyng to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alſo and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that euery perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonnes charged with the finding of any haquebut, and his or their ſeruaunte or ſeruaunts ſhall and may exerciſe and vſe ſhotynge in the ſame haquebut, at ſuch markes, as are limit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and appoynted by the ſtatute made in the .xxxiii. yeare of the taygne of kyng Henrye the eyght, or at their owne proper games, ſo that they carry not, or vſe not the ſame ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebut, in any hygh waye, vnleſſe it be comyng or goyng to or from the muſters, or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge towardes or from the ſeruyce of defence of the realme, any clauſe or article in the ſayde acte of the .xxxiii. yeare, to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes that thys acte ne any thynge therin conteyned, ſhal extende to charge any perſon or perſons, dwellyng or abydyng within the Countries of Northwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and Southwales, and wythin the County Palentine of Lancaſter, and Cheſter, or eyther of them, with the fyndynge or hauynge of anye haquebut, but that they and euerye of them, ſhal and maye at their wil, libertye, and pleaſure, haue and kepe, in ſtede and place of euery haquebut, charged by this acte, one longe bowe, &amp; one ſhefe of arrowes, ouer and beſides ſuche other armoure and munition as is by the lawes of thys realme limyted and appoynted, any thynge in this acte to the contrary notwythſtandynge.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes that the Lorde Chauncelor of England, or keper of the greate Seale for the tyme beinge, ſhall and maye from tyme to tyme by vertue of the Kynge and Quenes hyghnes Commiſſion, name, aſſigne, and appoynte Commyſſioners, in euery Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, Boroughe, and towne corporate, wherein ther be Iuſtices of the peace, aſwel in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande as in Wales, ſo many of the ſame Iuſtices of Peace, wyth ſuche and as manye other perſons to be ioyned wyth them dwelling out of the ſaid Cityes, Boroughes, and townes Corporate, as he or they ſhall thinke mete, to take vewe of armoure in euerye of the ſame Cities, Boroughes, and townes Corporate, according to this preſente acte, and alſo to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſygne what harnes and armoure ſhalbe prouided and kepte by the inhabitauntes of euery ſuch Citie, Boroughe, and towne Corporate as is aforeſaid, according to this preſent acte.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Kynge and the Quene.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="colophon">
            <p>EXCVSVM LONDINI IN AEDIBVS Iohannis Cavvodi, Tipographi Regiae Maieſtatis.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="privilege">
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
